<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Observations upon the oath enacted I. Eliz. commonly called the oath of supremacy for the better satisfaction of those that may finde themselves concerned therein.</title>
            <author>Winter, John, Sir, 1600?-1673?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66713</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3081</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11523</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12930166</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12930166</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95634</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66713)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95634)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 993:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Observations upon the oath enacted I. Eliz. commonly called the oath of supremacy for the better satisfaction of those that may finde themselves concerned therein.</title>
                  <author>Winter, John, Sir, 1600?-1673?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 17 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Winter. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Imprint taken from NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Royal supremacy (Church of England)</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95634:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95634:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>OBSERVATIONS UPON THE OATH Enacted 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> Commonly called, <hi>The OATH of S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PREMACY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the better ſatisfaction of thoſe that may finde themſelves concerned therein.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:95634:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95634:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Obſervations upon the <hi>Oath</hi> Enacted 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> commonly called, <hi>The Oath of S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PREMACY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y the Oath of Supremacy Enacted by <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, the ſaid King was ſworn to be Supreme Head of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Which title was of ſo great offence and ſcandal, even to ſome of thoſe that then profeſſed the Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that they writ Invectives againſt the ſame, as Romane Catholicks alſo did, and ſundry perſons loſt their lives in thoſe daies for denial thereof, as is written of Sir <hi>Thomas More,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>But that Oath was afterwards aboliſht by Parliament, with ſome other ſtatutes relating thereunto: and in the fifth year of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the enſuing Oath was enjoyned by an Act then entitled <hi>(All ancient Juriſdiction reſtored to the Crown, and all forreign power aboliſhed)</hi> the words of which Oath are as followeth,</p>
            <p>I A, B. <hi>do utterly teſtifie and declare in my conſcience, that the Queens Highneſſe is the only Supreme Governour of this Realm, of all other her Highneſſes Dominions and Countreys, as well in all Spirituall or Eccleſiaſtical things or Cauſes, as temporal,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That no forreign Prince, Perſon, Prelate, State or Potentate, hath, or ought to have any Juriſdiction, Power, Superiority, Prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, or Authority Eccleſiaſtical or Spiritual within this Realm, and therefore I do utterly renounce and forſake all forreign Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, Powers, Superiorities, and Authorities, and do promiſe that from henceforth I ſhall bear faith and true Allegiance to the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95634:3"/>Queens Highneſs, her Heirs and lawful Succeſsors, and to my pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſhall aſsiſt and defend all Juriſdictions, Priviledges, Prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencies and Authorities granted or belonging to the Queens High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, her Heirs and Succeſsors, or united and annexed to the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Crown of this Realm. So help me God, and by the Contents of this Book.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although the words of this Oath are not the ſame as in the former, <hi>and Supreme Head of the Church of England</hi> not parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly mentioned therein, yet according to the common accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the words in the ſaid Oath, it ſeemed to attribute to her ſaid Majeſty in effect and ſubſtance no leſs ſpiritual Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and power; (nay more) then what the ſaid former Oath did or might import. Wherefore this Oath was alſo excepted at by divers. In which conſideration, and for the clearing of doubts that might be conceived thereupon, her Majeſty by an <hi>Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in her <hi>Injunctions</hi> publiſhed afterwards in the ſaid firſt year of her Reign, did explain and interpret the ſence and meaning of the words of the ſaid Oath, in which the ſame ſhould from thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth be accepted and taken. The <hi>Admonition</hi> and <hi>Title</hi> is as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="admonition">
               <body>
                  <head>An Admonition to Simple men deceived by malicious.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Queens Majeſty being informed, that in certain places of the Realm ſundry of her native Subjects being called to Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Miniſtry in the Church, be by ſiniſter perſwaſion, and perverſe conſtruction, induced to finde ſome ſcruple in the form of an Oath, which by an Act of the laſt Parliament is preſcribed to be required of divers perſons for the Recognition of their Allegiance to her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, which certainly never was ne ever meant, nor by any equity of words or good ſence can be thereof gathered; would that all her lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Subjects ſhould underſtand, that nothing was, is, or ſhall be meant or intended by the ſame Oath, to have any other duty, allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, or bond required by the ſame Oath, then was acknowledged to be due to the moſt noble Kings of famous memory,</hi> K. Henry <hi>the</hi> 8. <hi>her Majeſties Father, or</hi> K. Edward <hi>the</hi> 6. <hi>her Majeſties Brother.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And further, <hi>her Majeſty forbiddeth all manner her Subjects, to give ear or credit to ſuch perverſe and malicious perſons, which moſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95634:3"/>ſiniſterly and maliciouſly labour to notifie to her loving Subjects, how by words of the ſaid Oath it may be collected, that the Kings or Queeus of this Realm, poſsſsors of the Crown, may challenge autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and power of Ministry, of Divine Service in the Church: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in her ſaid Subjects be much abuſed by ſuch evil diſpoſed perſons; for certainly her Majeſty neither doth, nor ever will challenge any other authority then that was challenged and lately uſed by the ſaid noble Kings of famous memory, K.</hi> Henry <hi>the Eighth, and K.</hi> Edward <hi>the ſixth, <hi>which is and was of ancient time due to the Imperiall Crown of this Realm,</hi>
                     </hi> THAT IS, <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God to have the Soveraignty and Rule over all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner perſons born within theſe Realms, Dominions and Countreys, of what eſtate either Eccleſiaſtical or tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſoever they be,</hi> SO AS <hi>no other forreign power ſhall or ought to have any ſuperiority over them. <hi>And if any perſon that hath conceived any other ſence of the form of the ſaid Oath, ſhall accept the ſame Oath with this Interpretation, ſence or meaning, her Majeſty is well pleaſed to accept every ſuch in that behalf, as her good and obedient Subjects, and ſhall acquit them of all manner penalties contained in the ſaid Act, againſt ſuch as ſhall peremptorily or obſtinately refuſe to take the ſame Oath.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>It is obſervable, that the Queen did thus explain and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret the words of this Oath by her own authority. But whereas ſome might then object, as others have done ſince, upon the ſame occaſion, that the words of an Oath could not be warrantably in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted from their ordinary ſence, and uſual acceptation, by any authority leſs then that of the Law-maker: Therefore the ſaid <hi>Admonition</hi> was confirmed by her ſaid Majeſty in Parliament, by the Satute 5 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1. wherein is this <hi>Proviſo</hi> as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Provided alſo, that the Oath expreſsed in the ſaid Act made in the ſaid firſt Year, ſhall be taken and expounded in ſuch form as is ſet forth in an Admonition annexed to the Queens Majeſties Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions publiſhed in the firſt Year of her Majeſties Reign; That is to ſay, to confeſse and acknowledge in her Majeſty, her Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, none other authority then that was challenged and lately uſed by the Noble</hi> K. Henry <hi>the</hi> 8. <hi>and</hi> K. Edward <hi>the</hi> 6. <hi>as in the ſaid admonition more plainly may appear.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:95634:4"/>
            <p> It is obſervable, that in vertue of this <hi>Proviſoe</hi> in the ſaid Statute, the aforeſaid <hi>admonition</hi> acquired the force of a Law as much as the <hi>Proviſoe</hi> it ſelf had, which referres to the ſaid <hi>admonition,</hi> and conſequently makes void in law whatſoever was formerly Enacted contrary to the ſame. So that from and after the ſaid Act 5. <hi>Eliz.</hi> the ſaid Oath (though pronounced in the form of words <hi>verbatim,</hi> as is expreſſed in the Act 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi>) yet the effect and tenour of the ſaid words muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued and underſtood in the <hi>form,</hi> and according to the <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, ſence and meaning,</hi> as appeareth in the aforeſaid <hi>admonition.</hi> And whoſoever upon tender of the ſaid Oath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, if (when he ſhall have read or pronounced the words thereof) he do profeſſe that he intends in ſwearing the ſame to mean thoſe ſaid words in no other ſence, but according as the <hi>admonition</hi> aforeſaid doth ſet forth, No Officer whatſoever can preſſe him to ſwear it any other waies. Which being mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Law the Learned in the Law can beſt reſolve, if any doubt be made thereof.</p>
            <p>The next Enquiry ſhall be, if any thing be contained in the ſaid <hi>admonition,</hi> either in words or meaning, which a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciencious perſon, Proteſtant, or Roman Catholike can juſtly except againſt.</p>
            <p>The Exceptions generally pretended againſt the ſame are, Firſt, That the ſaid Oath was purpoſely framed for profeſſion of Religion then newly eſtabliſhed. Secondly, That the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty and rule</hi> claimed by her Majeſty in the ſaid <hi>admonition</hi> is, over Eccleſiaſtical perſons, and in things and Cauſes ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and Eccleſiaſtical, both which (ſay moſt of thoſe that except againſt the ſame) are exempted <hi>(Jure divino)</hi> from the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the temporal Magiſtrate, and conſequently the King is in effect declared thereby to be Head of the Church. Thirdly, That the ſpiritual power and Juriſdiction left by Chriſt to his Church, and the reſpective Paſtors of the ſame, is likewiſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely denyed therein. Theſe things being part of their Faith and Religion, they cannot ſwear without renouncing the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95634:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſame, and giving ſcandal to others of their profeſſion, which therefore ſhall be the ſubject of our next Obſervations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The very words of this <hi>admonition</hi> do expreſs that the ſaid Oath was <hi>preſcribed and required for recognition of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Latitude of meaning which might be contained in the words of the Oath, <hi>viz. (Under God Supreme Governour, as well in Spirituall and Eccleſiaſtical things and Cauſes as temporal)</hi> is reſtrained in this <hi>admonition,</hi> by theſe words, <hi>viz. Her Majeſty neither doth nor ever will challenge any other authority then what was challenged and lately uſed by</hi> Henry <hi>the Eighth, and</hi> Edward <hi>the ſixth, which is and was of ancient time due to the Imperial Crown of this Realm.</hi> And then it is particularly ſpecified what that authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was by the words of the ſaid <hi>admonition</hi> immediatly following, <hi>viz.</hi> THAT IS <hi>under God to have the Soveraignty and Rule over all manner perſons born within thoſe her Realms, Dominions, and Countreys, of what eſtate either Eccleſiaſticall or Temporall ſoever they be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Leaſt by the ſaid Oath her Majeſty might ſeem to deny to the Church the Power and Juriſdiction left by Chriſt to his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and their Succeſſors, being <hi>meerly ſpirituall,</hi> her Majeſty therefore profeſſeth not to challenge authority or power of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of divine Service in the Church. And moreover reſtrains the denial of Spirituall and Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, Power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the ſaid Oath (being in general) to ſuch Juriſdiction (only) as was <hi>repugnant</hi> to the ſaid Soveraignty and Rule over all her Subjects. Which is apparent by theſe words, <hi>So as no other forraign power ſhall or ought to have any Superiority over them.</hi>] which words (SO AS) denote the reſt to be relative to her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties <hi>Superiority</hi> and <hi>Rule,</hi> that immediately before was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</p>
            <p>And in further proof thereof, Whereas the aforeſaid Act in the ſaid firſt Year of her Reign was entituled <hi>[All ancient Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons reſtored to the Crown, and all forreign power aboliſht,]</hi> the Statute made in the fifth Year of her Reign, <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. ſeemed to qualifie or explain the ſaid former Act, for it entitled the ſaid former Act to be an Act <hi>restoring to the Crown the ancient Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95634:5"/>ever the state Eccleſiastical and ſpiritual, and aboliſhing all forreign power</hi> REPUGNANT <hi>to the ſame.</hi> The alteration of the Title is very obſervable in this latter Act, for it ſeemed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to denote and explain that which in the heat of the then ſuddain change of Religion had not been ſo maturely diſgeſted and eſtabliſhed in the former.</p>
            <p>The Articles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and of the Clergy, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the Kings ſaid power and Authority by calling it the <hi>civil</hi> (not <hi>ſpiritual</hi>) ſword.</p>
            <p>Doctor <hi>Carleton</hi> afterwards Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter</hi> in his notable Treatiſe of<note n="*" place="margin">In his Ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monition to the Reader. <hi>The Fathers write for the ſpiritual Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of the Church above Princes,</hi> which thing we never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied.</note> 
               <hi>Juriſdictions Epiſcopal, Regal and Papal,</hi> writes moſt learnedly and clearly upon this Subject. He ſayes <hi>pag.</hi> 9. <q>As for ſpirituall Juriſdiction of the Church, ſtanding in Examination of Controverſies of Faith, judging of Hereſies, depoſing of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, Excommunication of notorious and ſtubborn offenders, Ordination of Prieſts and Deacons, Inſtitution and collation of Benifices and Spiritual Cures, <hi>&amp;c. which Princes cannot give nor take from the Church,</hi> this power hath been practiſed by the Church without coactive Juriſdiction other then of Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication. But when matters handled in the Eccleſiaſtical Conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry are not matters of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> but of a <hi>Civill</hi> nature which yet are called <hi>Eccleſiasticall,</hi> as being given by Princes, and appointed to be within the Cogniſance of that Conſiſtory, and when the Cenſures are not <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> but <hi>carnall, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſive, coactive,</hi> here appeareth the power of the Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 42, 43. It cannot be denyed, but that there is a Power in the Church, not only Internal but alſo of External Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Of Internal Power there is no queſtion made, External Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction being underſtood all that is practiſed in External Courts or Conſntories, is either Definitive or Mulctative. Authority Definitive in matters of Faith and Religion, belongeth to the Church; Mulctative Power may be underſtood either as it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to ſpiritual Cenſures, or as it is with Coaction. As it ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in ſpiritual Cenſures, it is the right of the Church, as was pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by the Church, when the Church was without a Chriſtian Magiſtrate and ſince. But Coactive Juriſdiction was never pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95634:5"/>by the Church, when the Church was without Chriſtian Magiſtrate, but was alwayes underſtood to belong to the Civill Magiſtrate, whether he were Chriſtian or Heathen. <hi>&amp;e.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>The Apoſtles did ſometimes take vengeance upon the diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, but that was not by the <hi>Material</hi> Sword, <hi>(in the Power whereof we place Coaction)</hi> but by the <hi>Spiritual</hi> Sword.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Learned Biſhop of <hi>Derry,</hi> lately made Biſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> and honour'd with the Title of Lord Primat of all <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſpeaks moſt clearly to this Point, in his Book <hi>Schiſm Guarded,</hi> p. 160. <q>But I expect it ſhould be Objected, that beſides theſe Statutes which concern the Patronage of the Engliſh Church, the Legiſlative, the Judiciary, the Diſpenſative Power of Popes, There are two other Statutes made by <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth. The one, <hi>An Act for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhing the Authority of the Biſhop of</hi> Rome: The other, <hi>An Act for eſtabliſhing the Kings Succeſsion in the Crown;</hi> wherein there is an Oath, That the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> ought not to have any Juriſdiction or Authority in this Realm. And that it is declared in the 37<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Article of our Church, That the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> hath no Juriſdiction in this Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi> And in the Oath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> That no forrein Prelate hath, or ought to have, any Juriſdiction or Authority, Eccleſiaſtical or Spiritual within this Realm.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>I Anſwer this Objection three wayes, Firſt, As to the two Laws of <hi>Henry</hi> the eigth, They are both repealed long ſince by Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and never were reſtored by any ſucceeding Prince. If there were any thing blame-worthy in them, let it dye with them. I confeſſe I approve not the Conſtruing of one Oath for another, nor the ſwearing before-hand to Statutes made or to be made, But <hi>de mortuis nil niſi bonum.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Secondly, I Anſwer according to the equity of my ſecond ground, that although it were ſuppoſed, that our Anceſtors had over-reached themſelves and the truth in ſome expreſſion; yet that concerns not us at all, ſo long as we keep our ſelves exactly to the line and level of Apoſtolical Tradition.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Thirdly and principally I anſwer, That our. Anceſtors meant the very ſame thing that we do, our only difference is in the uſe of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95634:6"/>words, <hi>Spiritual Authority or Juriſdiction,</hi> which we underſtand properly of authority and Juriſdiction, purely Spiritual, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth no further then the Court of Conſcience. But by Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Authority or Juriſdiction, they did underſtand Eccleſiaſtical authority and Juriſdiction in the Exteriour Court, which in truth is <hi>partly Spiri-tual, partly Political.</hi> So our Anceſtors caſt out <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Eccleſiaſtical Coactive Juriſdiction.</hi> The ſame do we, They did not take away from the Pope <hi>the Power of the Keys</hi> or <hi>Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction purely ſpiritual;</hi> No more do we. And <hi>p.</hi> 119. We ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that Biſhops were alwayes eſteemed the proper Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Cannons, both for compoſing of them, and executing of them; but with this Caution, that to make them Laws the confirmation of the Prince was required, and to give the Biſhop a Coactive Power to execute them, the Princes Grant or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion was needfull. And <hi>p.</hi> 170. Whatſoever Power our Laws did diveſt the Pope of, they inveſted the King with it. But they never inveſted the King with any Spiritual Power or Juriſdiction, witneſſe the Injunction of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the Articles of the Church, King <hi>James,</hi> our Statutes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>K</hi> James Triplict nodo, tripl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> cuncus. <hi>p. 47.</hi>
                  </note> In that Oath ONLY is conteined the Kings abſolute Power, to be Judge over all Perſons as well Civil as Eccleſiaſtical, exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all forrain Powers and Potentates to be Judges within his Dominions:</q> And generally all Engliſh-Proteſtant Writers who maintain the 39. Articles, with the Diſcipline and Canons of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> do conſtantly affirm.</p>
            <p>That the Kings ſaid Supreme <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Rule</hi> is intended no other wayes but to exerciſe under God <hi>the Supreme coactive Juriſdiction and Power over all his Subjects within his Realms and Dominions, of what eſtate ſoever they be, whether Eccleſiaſticall or Temporal, to take cogniſance in his externall Tribunals of offenders for the puniſhing of them with civil and corporal puniſhments, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the nature and quality of their reſpective offences:</hi> And that Spirituall and Eccleſiaſticall things and Cauſes (the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors wherein are lyable to his cogniſance and puniſhment as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) are not meant of things and cauſes that are meerly ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, as of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> but of ſuch as in their own nature are either <hi>civil or mixed with ſomething that is temporal,</hi> which accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95634:6"/>to vulgar acceptation, are called nevertheleſſe <hi>Spirituall</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> for the reaſons noted by Doctor <hi>Carleton</hi> as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
            <p>This Supreme external Coactive power and Juriſdiction as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, cannot be acknowledged to be due to the King, but by neceſſary conſequence all Power, Prerogative, Juriſdiction, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority or Authority repugnant to the ſame, muſt be denied and diſclaimed in any Prelate, Perſon, State, or Potentate, forreign or domeſtick whatſoever, other then by or under his Majeſties permiſſion or Authority.</p>
            <p>But it is alſo obſervable, that what Power or Juriſdiction ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever that is but meerly Spiritual (and conſequently not belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the King) is not meant or intended to be denied or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced to the Church, or to any Perſon Prelate <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, as the aforeſaid Biſhop of <hi>Derry</hi> moſt expreſly declares, in very many places, of his Book aforeſaid, which for brevities ſake, are omitted, excepting theſe few hereunder mentioned, which may abundantly ſatisfie. <hi>Pag.</hi> 62. <hi>And therefore when we meet with theſe words, or the like,</hi> That <hi>No forreign Prelate ſhall exerciſe any manner of power, Juriſdiction, Superiority, Preheminence or priviledge Eccleſiaſtical or Spiritual within this Realm; It is not to be understood of Internal or purely Spirituall power in the Court of Conſcience, or the power of the Keys (We ſee the contrary practiſed every day) but of external coactive pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in Eccleſiaſtical cauſes,</hi> in foro contentioſo, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And in his Epiſtle to the Reader, (having ſet down all or the moſt conſiderable Points of difference and queſtion upon this Subject, concludes his ſaid Epiſtle with theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q>The true controverſie is, Whether the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> ought by <hi>Divine Right</hi> to have the external regiment of the Engliſh Church, and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>active Juriſdiction in Engliſh Courts, againſt the will of the King, and Laws of the Kingdome. And <hi>p.</hi> 218. No dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between Romane Catholicks and our ſelves about the Papacy, but only about the extent of Papal power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>To theſe may be added, that the Biſhop of <hi>Spalato</hi> that came into <hi>England,</hi> after his being conſecrated Biſhop by the Pope,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95634:7"/>or by authority from the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> did not renue his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter after he came over, yet (as is well known) ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed divers Prieſts here, which was never diſputed, but allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Church of <hi>England</hi> to have been validly done. All which confirms what is ſaid before, That Juriſdiction purely ſpirituall is not denied by the now intendiment of the ſaid Oath, and that it is not an Oath of Religion, but of Allegiance, as is expreſly ſaid in Queen <hi>Elizabeths Admonition</hi> aforeſaid, and obliges the takers to no more, but to aſſiſt and defend all the ancient Juriſdictions of the Crown, and to renounce and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugn all forreign Juriſdictions and Powers repugnant to the ſame. What thoſe ancient Juriſdictions of the Crown were eſteemed to be, may be obſerved by the Statutes of <hi>Clarendon,</hi> the Statute of <hi>Carlile,</hi> the Articles of the Clergy, the Statute of Proviſors, and other the Laws of our <hi>Norman</hi> Kings, and in the times of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt, <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, which Statutes and Laws had not ſo publickly paſſed, without a greater clamour of other Nations profeſſing the ſame Religion, if the Popes pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed power in thoſe reſpective mixed caſes had been thought to have been <hi>Jure divino,</hi> or ſo undeniably his right, as ſome Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines do chalenge in his behalf.</p>
            <p>But foraſmuch as many Learned and Large Treatiſes have been written upon this Subject, of mixed Cauſes, as aforeſaid, both by Romane Catholicks, and by Profeſſors of the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Religion of ſeveral Nations, and of each ſide ſome holding that they belong to the Kings Supreme Authority and civil ſword, others that they belong only to the Church without any Conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from the temporal Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>For allay to the Scruples that may hereupon ariſe in the mindes of any his Majeſties Loyal Subjects, it may be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that ſince the Learned Doctors of both ſides do reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare upon mature conſideration of ſeveral Texts of holy Writ; Acts of Councils, and other reaſons alledged, to have diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95634:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>Sentiments therein, ſome of each ſide, holding the contrary to what others of the ſame profeſſion do ſtrongly maintain, but never determined by the Church:</p>
            <p>The probability of their ſaid opinions may reſpectively warrant (if not oblige) all his Majeſties Subjects (eſpecially being ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by Law) to acknowledge ſubmiſſion to that external co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>active Power and Authority of his Majeſty for the puniſhment of Offenders with civil and corporal puniſhments in ſuch mixed ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as aforeſaid, which their reſpective Teachers doe affirm to be juſtly derived from natural Reaſon, and clear places of Scripture, and aſſert them as part of his Royal Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>Our ancient Hiſtories, Statutes, and moſt authentick Records of former times, long before <hi>Henry</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> do teſtifie as aforeſaid, That our Kings did challenge a ſovereign, external, coactive Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction over all their Subjects, as aforeſaid in thoſe caſes, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times indulging them to the Eccleſiaſtical Courts, and See of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſometimes reſtraining them again (of their own Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, without recourſe to the Pope or See of <hi>Rome</hi>) more or leſſe according to their zeal or devotion towards the Church and Church-men, and the reſpective occaſions in thoſe times, according as was then thought fit by our Kings and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Read the Statutes of Proviſors, 25. of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>The practice in <hi>France</hi> ſufficiently declares what that Kings Power is in the caſes aforeſaid: For although ſpiritual offences (that are meerly ſuch) are puniſhable in the Eccleſiaſtical Courts onely by ſpiritual Cenſures as Excommunication, Suſpenſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet if the cauſe be mixed in any ſort with what is civil or temporal, as aforeſaid; or if never ſo little pecuniary Mulct be impoſed upon the offenders for damages by the Eccleſiaſtical Judges, the whole matter may be brought to the cognizance of the civil Court upon appeal, and the former ſentence reverſed, if it be thought fit: Nor does any Eccleſiaſtical Promotion or Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, how great ſoever, priviledge any perſon from civil and corporal puniſhments there; if he offend againſt the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95634:8"/>the now Arch-biſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi> under the moſt Chriſtian Kings, who is known to be moſt zealouſly devoted to the Church and See of <hi>Rome.</hi> And many other Preſidents of the ſame nature have been in <hi>Hungary, Germany,</hi> and other Countreys that hold communion with that Church.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Spain</hi> exerciſes the like Authority in ſeveral pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his Dominions, and ſo amply in his Kingdome of <hi>Sicily,</hi> that it is there called, <hi>Supream Spiritual Authority,</hi> and <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Monarchy,</hi> as is acknowledged by the Catholick Divine in in his Anſwer to the fifth part of S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Edward Cookes</hi> Reports, <hi>pag.</hi> 102. which words <hi>Supream, ſpiritual Authority,</hi> and <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Monarchy</hi> ſound as harſh, and require a favourable explanation, no leſſe than any the words in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Oath aforeſaid. He ſayes indeed, <q>That Pope <hi>Urbane</hi> grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſame long time ſince to that Kings Predeceſſours, as Pope <hi>Nicolas</hi> ſomewhat of the like nature to St. <hi>Edward</hi> King of <hi>England.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But meer ſpiritual Juriſdiction (as is conceived) could not be granted to a Lay perſon. And our Queſtion being of the original right of our Princes to ſupream, external, coactive Juriſdiction over their Subjects to take cognizance of offenders in ſuch mixed caſes, as aforeſaid, for puniſhing them with civil and corporal pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments according to the reſpective quality of their offences, which (indeed) is no other but a civil and temporal power, though the ſaid caſes be vulgarly called <hi>Spiritual</hi> for the reaſons declared as aboveſaid, he ought to have told us how the Pope came to be inveſted with ſuch coactive power by force of Law and corporall puniſhments, which he ſo granted away unto others.</p>
            <p>Chriſt ſaid, <hi>His Kingdome was not of this world.</hi> The Apoſtles claimed no ſuch coactive power, by force of Law, and corporal pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, as aforeſaid, nor any the aforeſaid exemption of their perſons or goods from the temporal Magiſtrate and his Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals. The Church (as the ſaid Catholike Divine confeſſes) had no ſuch power for ſeveral Ages, the Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> was the firſt that granted it, who did it (to uſe his words) <hi>volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily.</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:95634:8"/>And other Kings and Princes, <hi>upon their ſingular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, and in imitation of that good Emperour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And doth not all this plainly ſignifie, that the External Coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive power (ſuch as aforeſaid) was originally in the Supreme temporal Magiſtrate? whoſe ſaid Supreme power (as moſt Learned men do affirm) cannot binde and conclude it ſelf in a Law, ſo as not to be able to revoke or alter the ſame when there is juſt cauſe, for preſervation of its being, and generall good of the Common-wealth (otherways) in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent danger. And conſequently howſoever Cannon Laws and Decretals have been ſometimes received by permiſſion or conceſſion of our Kings alone, or Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our Nation, and in vertue of ſuch reception (and not otherwiſe) matriculated among our Laws, yet according to the Preſident of many of our Kings and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments long before King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, the ſame might be <hi>validly</hi> reſtrained or made void to this Nation, ſo farre as to the nature of a Law, if our ſaid Kings and Parliaments conceived it neceſſary for thoſe reaſons as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ſaid. Whether the ſame was well or ill done by them, or whether the cauſes were ſufficient or not, in the reſpective occaſions, the doers were anſwerable in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, not their Subjects who were bound to yeeld obedience to their Soveraign power, in what things ſoever were not purely Spirituall, or repugnant unto the Law of God.</p>
            <p>Since therefore it is moſt apparant, that Spiritual Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity (it ſelf) is not denied by the intendment of this Oath explained by the Admonition and declared as aforeſaid (which is otherwiſe then the aboveſaid Catholick Divine did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it to be; but only the enlargement of Spirituall Authority to temporal coaction (ſuch as aforeſaid,) which (in reality) alters its nature, and is repugnant to the prerogative Royall of this Crowne, and which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Court of <hi>Rome (not the Church of Rome)</hi> and ſome Divines moſt eſpecially depending upon the ſame
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95634:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>would extend the ſaid ſpirituall power unto, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Jure Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vino,</hi> but was not ſo <hi>ab initio,</hi> as manifeſtly appears by what is aboveſaid.</p>
            <p>Why ſhould any his Majeſties Loyall Subjects (Romane Catholikes eſpecially) deny to acknowledge their dutifull ſubmiſſion to his Majeſties ſaid Soveraignty and Rule over all his Subjects, and their like obedience to maintain Laws eſtabliſhed, ſo farre as they relate to his ſaid Authority in ſuch manner as above declared; Whereas not only the Opinions of many of the moſt Learned Writers of their own Religion doe maintain, That Externall Coaction by force of Law, and civil and corporall puniſhment upon of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders of what quality ſoever, and for what matter or cauſe ſoever ſo deſerving, as aboveſaid, is of naturall right belonging to the Supreme Temporal Magiſtrate, But alſo, the practiſe of our Kings and Parliaments in former Ages (time out of minde) as alſo the preſent practiſe of other Kings and Countreys, that (nevertheleſſe) hold Communion with the Pope and Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> do au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſe and approve the exerciſe of the ſame, according to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergent occaſions, by the ſaid Supreme temporall Magiſtrate, in manner as aboveſaid.</p>
            <p>Let them not therefore give juſt advantage to their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries in Religion, to preſſe againſt them the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the penal Statutes, by objecting that what they ſuffer is upon ſuſpicion of a dangerous dependency upon a forreigne State, but not for any Doctrine or Point of Religion, which their Church hath declared to be of Faith.</p>
            <p>The unlimitted power, and immoderate attributes given to Popes by Cannoniſts, and ſome other Writers of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Authority of that ſide, together with the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent proceedings of ſome Popes thereupon, have been prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally the occaſion, that the ſaid Oath hath been ſo ſtrictly ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Catholicks, and hath chiefly cauſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:95634:9"/>with that See, and by the over-bold aſſertions of ſuch Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that ſome of their ſaid Opinions were <hi>De Fide,</hi> it hath been inſtilled (though not with truth) into the minds of moſt of the people of this Nation, That whoſoever holds Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> muſt neceſſarily be princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled according to their ſaid Tenets. Which cauſed his Majeſty King <hi>James</hi> (and others ſo conceiving) to think that the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ſaid Oath was purpoſly framed to make diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Proteſtants and Roman Catholicks, who chiefly upon this ſcore were all promiſcuouſly called Papiſts, and ſo ſevere Laws Enacted againſt them in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time and ſince. B<hi rend="sub">p</hi> of <hi>Derry</hi>'s <hi>Schiſm Garded. Page</hi> 176. <q>It is true there are other differences between us, but this is the main difference that giveth denomination to the parties.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But the truth hereof ought (if but in charity) to be further enquired into by all conſcientious men, eſpecially by thoſe in Authority.</p>
            <p>For many of the Roman Catholicks of theſe Nations (nay moſt of the moſt-knowing among them) do profeſſe, againſt ſuch over-bold aſſertions, ſuch immoderate attributes, ſuch unlimited powers and practices, as much as any Proteſtants whatſoever. And although they hold Communion with the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>ſpiritualibus,</hi> and acknowledg (as their Ancient Forefathers did) that the Pope is the Supreme Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Paſtor (which the Biſhop of <hi>Derry</hi> ſaies is not medled with one way or other in the intendment of this Oath, ſo it be but in ſpirituals. And his Royal Majeſty King<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Apol.</hi> for the Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, <hi>p.</hi> 46.</note> 
               <hi>James</hi> could be content that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> were <hi>Patriarck of the Weſt, and were the firſt Biſhop among all Biſhops, and</hi> Princeps Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coporum, <hi>ſo as he be no otherwiſe then as</hi> Peter <hi>was</hi> Princeps Apoſtolorum.) Yet the ſaid Roman Catholicks do not hold it as a part of their faith, that the Pope is infallibly free from Error, or that he can abſolve Subjects from their obedience to their natural Prince, or from the Obligation of faithfull upright dealing with their Neighbours, though ſuch their Prince or Neighbour be not of their Religion, or were Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95634:10"/>or what more the Pope could do by himſelf, or with any other, againſt them for that cauſe. And all this (ſay they) they will chearfully teſtifie upon their Oaths, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out equivocation or mental reſervation, if an Oath in clear terms expreſſing as aforeſaid be tendred unto them.</p>
            <p>It is not the true meaning of the Oath explained in manner as aboveſaid, which makes many of them refuſe to take the ſame; but there being an Oath made ſince, and called the Oath of Allegiance, makes them apprehend, that ſomething more than meer Allegiance is contained in the former. And beſides the latitude of the words in this Oath (at which many Proteſtants alſo ſtick) which words are not explained but by the admonition as aforeſaid, and that admonition again not cleared, but by the Writings of Learned Doctors, and then authorized by the Proviſo 5<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
               <hi>Eliz.</hi> and the force of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſo to be reſolved by the Learned Men in the Law. Theſe particulars (not known to many, and ſo intricate in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) and above all, the conſtant tendring of the ſaid Oath for ſo many years paſt, without the aforeſaid explanation. Theſe things I ſay have made it to be firmly believed by them, and thoſe of their profeſſion over all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that in taking the ſaid Oath, with what explanation ſoever (if ſuch explanation be not as publickly made known and declared) they give juſt ſcandal (which is <hi>Malum in ſe</hi>) that they renounce their Religion: as indeed the common acceptation of the words of the ſaid Oath do import no leſſe.</p>
            <p>And ſince the ſaid Roman Catholicks have been ſo Loyall to his Majeſty, not one having drawn Sword againſt him in the late Rebellion, ſo many of them having loſt their lives and eſtates, and endured ſtrict Impriſonment and great hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip for his cauſe, and rendred eminent ſervices in the late Wars even to the preſervation of his moſt <hi>Sacred Perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeems but very reaſonable what is generally deſire oy them, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Oathes required of them under ſo great penalties, may be cleared of thoſe doubtful expreſſions in them,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95634:10"/>which cauſe their ſcruples as aforeſaid, or a new Oath to be compiled in clear terms, whereby not only they, but alſo many Proteſtants who likewiſe ſcruple at the words of the ſame, may (to the entire ſatisfaction of his Majeſty and the Nation) fully teſtifie the Allegiance and Fidelity of faithful Subjects, and true Patriotts, and no longer remain (as generally they now do) diſtruſted, and ſubject to much obloquy, and in an incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city to ſerve their King and Countrey, (notwithſtanding the indulgence generally afforded to tender Conſciences, though of different perſwaſion from the Tenets of the Church of <hi>England,</hi>) and all this upon no other ſcore, but of being thought otherwiſe principled then what their ſaid late acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have approved them to be, and what they now offer to profeſſe upon their Oaths, which is the greateſt ſecurity that can be given in teſtimony of a mans intention, and as much as ſatisfies in the like caſe of ſuſpicion, from thoſe that have fought, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> againſt his Majeſty and been his moſt bitter enemies.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
